### **John Dawson**

429 Market Street Elmwood Park, NJ 07407 201.703.1116 johndaw@gotnet.com

### **Summary**

I have over 25 years experience in business, both as a business owner/investor and as a member of corporate America. I've spent 20 years in the clinical laboratory industry, joining Bio Reference Labs in 2001 as Sales Director, SE, after a leveraged acquisition of Laboratory Corporation of America. As Sales Director, I was responsible for an annual sales budget in excess of \$300 million, largest book of business within the corporation. I hired and developed a sales team of over 120 professionals. My sales organization exceeded budget and forecast each year in both price and volume. Prior to BRLI, I held several senior level sales and sales management positions with LCA. Throughout my career, I've set numerous national sales records and have been recognized at the highest levels for my accomplishments.

### **Professional Experience**

### **Self Employed**

04-present

Business ownership in the environmental industry, mechanical contracting, and professional services.

### Bio Reference Labs, Inc.

02-03 **Business Development.** Point person for coordinating/closing all non-traditional business relationships in the Central Region including physician networks, hospital delivery systems and independent laboratories. Worked closely with managed care, hospital, and physician sales teams in education, identification, presentation, negotiation and closing skills.

### RESULTS

2002 - \$3.4M 2003 - \$4.4M run rate as of Oct 31.

99-02 Director of Sales. Responsible for strategic planning and implementation of corporate goals and local initiatives, top and bottom line growth vs. price, volume and operating margin. Consisted of @ \$300M book of business with 120 FTE's including 9 District Business Managers, 2 Strategic Account Executives, 2 Genomics and Esoteric Testing Specialists, 7 Billing Information Specialists, Account Executives, Account Managers, Internal Account Managers, and Sales Support positions in the Atlanta/Southeast Business Unit, the second largest Business Unit within BRLI. Geography included North Carolina, South Carolina, Tennessee, Alabama, North Mississippi, and Georgia.

### RESULTS

Exceeded sales budget and forecast each year. Achieved growth objectives in both price and volume. Worked closely with Managing Director to achieve OM in excess of 20% each year.

### Bio Reference Labs, Inc.

97-99 **Senior District Sales Manager.** Responsible for sales and service in the GA physician market, SBCL's largest District.

### **RESULTS**

1999 #1 in the country new sales (Net After Assigned Disallowance)

1998 #1 in the country new sales (NAAD)- \$7.9M over budget

1997 #1 in the country new sales (NAAD)

94-96 **District Sales Manager.** Managed areas including GA, TN, SC, NC.

### RESULTS

1996 #2 in the country new sales (NAAD) - Record \$10M over budget

92-94 **Senior Hospital Territory Sales Manager.** Sales rep for middle and south GA in hospital market. Involved in business development activities in the district.

### RESULTS

Consistently in top 5% in the country with new sales @ \$1M per year.

83-91 **Territory Sales Manager.** Sold to hospitals, physicians, and industrial clients in TN, MS, KY.



### **RESULTS**

Consistently ranked at the top of the district and region.

Achievements
5 Time President's Club Winner 9 Time MVP Numerous Singular Achievement Awards Impact Award Winner/SelecTest Rollout

Education
BBA, Accounting Princeton University, 1982



## **JOHN DAWSON**

429 Market Street | Elmwood Park, NJ 07407 | johndaw@gotnet.com | 201.703.1116

### SENIOR SALES EXECUTIVE

### Hard-wired to proactively lead and perform at the highest levels

**President's Award Winning Sales Executive** with the big picture vision, leadership, and tenacity to successfully penetrate new markets, capture market share, and accelerate top and bottom-line revenue growth. Recognized for ability to build, guide, and sustain successful sales teams. Time and again, present proven accomplishments in goal-oriented sales management through expertise in business development and strategic planning capabilities. Excellent presentation, negotiation, closing, and follow through skills with a strong ability to build an industry presence. Available for travel and relocation. *Core competencies include:* 

- Revenue, Profit, Market Share Growth
- Budgeting, Planning, Forecasting
- Staff Leadership & Performance Enhancement
- Team Building, Coaching, Mentoring
- Strategic Account Acquisition & Management
- Executive Negotiations & Presentations
- Innovative Sales & Marketing Initiatives
- New Business Development
- Competitive Analysis & Product Positioning
- Analytical & Conceptual Problem Solving

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

NEWCASTLE TIRE RECYCLING, LLC., New Castle, DE

2004 - 2006

Start-up company specializing in alternative uses for tires and byproduct.

### **PRESIDENT**

Founded entrepreneurial company focused on providing mechanical contracting services to the environmental industry. Secured \$2 million in start-up capital. Scope of responsibility included all core executive leadership, operating management, sales, marketing, human resources, and finance. Led team of 40 employees at multiple ports and shipping yards across Southern and Mid-Atlantic states.

- Accelerated revenue growth from zero to \$1 million in 2 years.
- Landed key contract with State of Louisiana strengthening company's viability as acquisition candidate; successfully negotiated profitable sale of company.

BIO REFERENCE LABS, INC., Elmwood Park, NJ

1999 - 2002

Lleading provider of diagnostic testing, information and services; a Fortune 500 company (NASDAQ: <u>BRLI</u>) with 41,500 employees and \$5.5 billion in annual sales revenue.

### **DIRECTOR OF BUSINESS DEVELOPMENT, CENTRAL REGION, 2002 - 2003**

Directed all Business Development activities for Clinical and Anatomical Testing across Central Region. Served as point of coordination and closing for non-traditional business relationships encompassing Hospital Delivery Systems, Physician Networks, and Independent Laboratories.

- Delivered \$7.8 million in new business in 2 years.
- Increased Central Region market growth by 19%.

### **DIRECTOR OF SALES, SOUTHEAST BUSINESS UNIT, 1999 – 2002**

continued...



## JOHN DAWSON — Page 2

Led BRLI's second largest business unit comprised of 9 District Sales Managers, 2 Business Development Managers, 2 Genomic and Esoteric Testing Managers, 7 Billing Information Specialists, and 120 FTE's, realizing \$399 million in annual sales revenue. Managed development and implementation of integration strategy following acquisition of Laboratory Corporation of America.

- Successfully integrated BRLI and LCA sales forces and client bases of 13.000 clients across NC, SC, TN, GA, MS, and AL.
- Salvaged BC/BS contract valued at \$34 million— the largest contract in the Southeast.
- Reduced attrition rate to less than 1%, saving company \$10 million.
- Served as Six Sigma Trainer, Owner, and Champion, resulting in first year savings of \$1.65 million for Billing DSO and \$1.7 million for Account Profitability.
- Achieved all Price and Volume growth objectives; exceeded sales budgets and forecasts for three consecutive years.
- Recognized with the "Six Sigma Impact" award for Integration Sales plan and execution.
- Worked closely with Managing Director, achieving OM in excess of 20% each year.

BIO REFERENCE LABS, INC., New York City, NY

1983 - 1999

Leading provider of diagnostic testing and services; acquired by LCA in 1999.

### SENIOR DISTRICT SALES MANAGER, PHYSICIAN MARKET, 1997 - 1999

- Managed regional sales force for Physician Market comprised of 1 District Sales Manager and 23 FTE's charged with expanding revenue base of \$100 million.
- Achieved #1 district in the U.S. in 1997, 1998, 1999 for new sales productivity.
- **Served on national "Selectest" team** charged with the development and rollout of new pricing models; assumed regional leadership for launch following successful pilot.
- Led national Healtheon DX pilot program, resulting in company-wide product launch; product became primary IT product offering.
- Ramped up numerous sales and service initiatives including A/R UPIN, saved \$270,000;
   MLCP Reduction, netted \$359,000; and Call & Reporting Process, adopted as best practice.
- Five time recipient of the "President's Club Award".

### **DISTRICT SALES MANAGER, SOUTHEAST REGION, 1994 - 1996**

- Managed regional sales force of 11 Physician Account Managers and 1 Sales Support Specialist across GA, TN, SC, and NC.
- Ranked #2 in the U.S. for new sales; exceeded annual sales budget by \$10 million.

### EARLY CAREER PROGRESSION:

Senior Territory Sales Manager (1992-1994); Territory Sales Manager (1983 – 1992).

### **EDUCATION**

# Bachelor of Business Administration, Accounting NAIA Golf Champion

PRINCETON UNIVERSITY, Princeton, New Jersey

